Marc Gaede Papers, 1910-1999.: Finding Aid C1436
Manuscripts Division
- Photographic Prints, 1971-1997; 14 boxes
  - Bordertowns, 1980 March-1987; 2 boxes
    - Run over by a Drunk, Gallup, undated; 1 item (Box P-000065, Item 18)
      Depicts a heavily bleeding man (possibly dead) lying on the ground near a fallen street sign in front of a Gallup municipal building. A police officer stands next to his body. Includes a discarded landscape print on the reverse side.
    - Veteran's Cemetery, Window Rock, Arizona, 1987 June; 1 item (Box P-000065, Item 19)
    - Donna - Gallup, 1982 August; 1 item (Box P-000065, Item 20)
    - Gallup, New Mexico, undated; 1 item (Box P-000065, Item 21)
    - Gallup Police - Inspection Day, 1987 August; 1 item (Box P-000065, Item 22)
    - El Presidente, Looking, Gallup, 1986 November; 1 item (Box P-000065, Item 23)
    - Signs in Window - Rose Tree Bar - Flagstaff, 1980 August; 1 item (Box P-000065, Item 24)
  - Images from the Great West, 1986-1989; 6 boxes
    Consists of mounted 8x10", 11x14", 15x19", and 20x24" photographs that appeared in Images from the Great West (Chaco Press, 1990). They primarily depict landscapes in Montana, Wyoming, Idaho, western North and South Dakota, and northern Utah and Colorado, as well as portraits of authors, artists, and ranchers living in those areas.
    - Flathead Lake, Montana, 1988 April; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 1)
    - Wounded Knee - Pine Ridge Sioux Reservation, South Dakota, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 2)
    - Crow Battle Petroglyphs, Joliet, Montana, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 3)
      Reproduction Print (Stain).
    - Confluence of the Jefferson (top) and the Madison (bottom) Rivers to form the Missouri River, Three Forks, Montana, 1988; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 4)
      Photograph is uncaptioned. Reverse side contains discarded print of a landscape with a wooden house.
    - Mission Caborra, Sonora, 1986 January; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 5)
      Printed 1986. 1st Print.
    - Church, Ringling, Montana, 1988; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 6)
      Printed 1988.
    - Pryor Mountains, Montana, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 7)
      Taken from Wyoming. Printed 1989.
    - Salmon River between Chalis and Salmon, Idaho, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 8)
    - The Main Range below Browning, Montana, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 9)
    - Marias Massacre Site, Montana, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 10)
    - Granite Peak & Swiftcurrent Lake, Glacier National Park, Montana, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 11)
      Also includes a crossed out print of petroglyphs on the reverse side of the mount board.
    - Wickiup in Snow, Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 12)
      Also includes a rejected print of Church, Ringling, Montana on the reverse side of the mount board.
    - Chief Joseph Battleground of the Bear Paw Mountains, Montana, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 13)
    - Yellowstone River (Frozen), 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 14)
    - Oregon Trial Ruts - South Pass, Wyoming, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 15)
    - Washita Battlefield, Oklahoma, 1988 February; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 16)
      Black Kettle's Second Camp.
    - Custer Battlefield from Calhoun Ridge, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 17)
    - South Pass in Snow, Wyoming, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 18)
    - Mountain Meadows, Utah, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 19)
    - Deer Park & Yampa River, Colorado, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 20)
    - Cabins, Northern Utah, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 21)
    - Geysers near Old Faithful, Yellowstone National Park, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 22)
    - Wickiup Cave near Dillon, Montana, 1988 May; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 23)
    - Big Horn Mountains, Wyoming, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 24)
    - Confluence of Yellowstone (upper left) & Missouri (upper right) Rivers, North Dakota, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 25)
    - The Mission School, Blackfoot Reservation, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 26)
    - The Sawtooth Mountains, Idaho, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 27)
    - Lost River Mountains, Idaho, 1988; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 28)
    - Missouri River above Fort Benton, Montana (Carter's Ferry), 1988; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 29)
    - Missouri River at Judith Landing, Montana, 1987 April; 1 item (Box P-000066, Item 30)
    - Last Smoke of the Clover, Mist Fire, Yellowstone, 1988 October; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 1)
    - Crow Battle Petroglyphs, Joliet, Montana, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 2)
    - Grand Canyon of the, Yellowstone, 1988 April; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 3)
    - Yellowstone Lake, 1988 April; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 4)
    - Midway Geyser Basin and Fimhole River, Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 5)
    - Bear Lake, Utah, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 6)
      Print A of A and B. Printed 1989.
    - East Glacier, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 7)
    - Buffalo Jump, Two Medicine River, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 8)
    - West Glacier National Park, 1986; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 9)
    - Wickiup Garden Creek, Ruby Mountains, Montana, 1988; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 10)
    - Walker Lake, Nevada, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 11)
      Print B of A and B. Printed 1989.
    - Walker Lake, Nevada, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 12)
    - Custer Battlefield and Wolf Mountains, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 13)
    - Fine Damage, Yellowstone, 1988 October; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 14)
    - Fire Damage, Yellowstone, near Virginia Cascade, 1988 October; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 15)
    - Fire Damage, Yellowstone, 1988 October; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 16)
    - Bear Lake, Utah and Wyoming, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 17)
    - The Great Salt Lake, Utah, from Lakeside Mountains, 1988; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 18)
    - Confluence of the Madison Bottom and Jefferson Rivers, Three Forks, Montana, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 19)
    - St. Mary Lake, Glacier, National Park, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 20)
    - Shore Scene, Great Salt Lake, Utah (Statten Island), 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 21)
    - Brooks Lake, Wyoming, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 22)
    - Big Belt Mountains, Montana, 1988; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 23)
    - Box Elder Canyon on the Salmon River, Idaho, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 24)
      B of Series A and B
    - Shield Pictograph, Cottonwood Canyon, near Joliet, Montana, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 25)
    - Shield Pictograph, near Joliet, Montana, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 26)
    - Box Elder Canyon on the Salmon River, Idaho, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 27)
      A of series of A and B
    - Beaverhead Rock, Montana, 1988 April; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 28)
    - Independence Rock, Wyoming, 1988 March; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 29)
      Printed April 1988.
    - Untitled Landscape, undated; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 30)
    - The North, South Trail of the Main Teton Range, Montana, 1987; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 31)
    - New Fork Lake, Wyoming, 1988 October; 1 item (Box P-000067, Item 32)
    - Sioux Petroglyphs, Bull Mountain, South Dakota, undated; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 1)
    - Sheep Creek Wickiup near Dillon, Montana, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 2)
    - Custer Cavalry Inscription and Sioux Petroglyph, Cave Hills, South Dakota, 1989; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 3)
    - Crow Bear Petroglyphs, Joliet, Montana, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 4)
      Reproduction Print, Stains 1
    - Pond, near Earthquake Lake, Montana, 1986; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 5)
    - The Wind River, Wyoming, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 6)
    - Gates of Lodore, Colorado, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 7)
    - The Big Blackfoot River, near Clear Water Junction, Montana, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 8)
    - Martin's Cove and Sweetwater Valley, Wyoming, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000068, Item 9)
    - Marias Massacre Site, Montana, undated; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 1)
      Unmounted 11 x 14" print.
    - Custer Officer Major Joseph Tilford Inscription and Sioux Indian Petroglyph, South Dakota, undated; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 2)
    - J. Bridger Inscription, Green River Crossing, Wyoming, 1989 July; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 3)
    - William Clark Inscription, Pompeys Pillar, Montana, 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 4)
    - David Lavender, 1986 May; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 5)
    - Irving and Jean Stone, Beverly Hills, California, 1988; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 6)
    - Tee Pee Circles, Southern Mission Lake, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 7)
    - Dan Cushman, Great Falls, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 8)
    - Seattle, Washington, Ivan Doig, 1988 April; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 9)
    - Alston Chase, Livingston, Montana, 1989 July; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 10)
    - Custer Troops Inscription, North Dakota, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 11)
    - Custer Troops Inscription, North Dakota, 1988 December; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 12)
    - James Welch with dog Frank, Missoula, Montana, undated; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 13)
    - James Welch and Frank, Missoula, Montana, 1987 April; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 14)
      Printed 1987.
    - A.B. Guthrie, Jr., Montana, 1987 April; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 15)
    - Evan Connell, Sauselito, California, undated; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 16)
    - Evan Connell, 1988 April; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 17)
    - Norman Maclean - Chicago, Illinois, 1987 December; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 18)
    - Jim Harrison, Michigan, 1987 December; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 19)
    - A.B. Guthrie, Jr. and Miles Gaede, Chouteau, Montana, 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 20)
    - Wallace Stegner, Palo Alto, California, 1988 April; 1 item (Box P-000069, Item 21)
    - East Glacier, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box Z-000003, Item 1)
    - Saint Mary's Lake in Winter, Glacier National Park, 1988 January; 1 item (Box Z-000003, Item 2)
    - Sand Creek Massacre Site, Colorado, 1988; 1 item (Box Z-000003, Item 3)
    - The Marias Massacre Site, Montana, 1987 April; 1 item (Box Z-000003, Item 4)
    - The North South Trail of the Main Range, Montana, 1987 April; 1 item (Box Z-000003, Item 5)
    - Grand Tetons, 1987; 1 item (Box Z-000003, Item 6)
    - Untitled Photograph of Jagged Mountain Range with Valley in Foreground, undated; 1 item (Box Z-000003, Item 7)
    - Untitled Photograph of Jagged Mountain Range with Valley in Foreground, undated; 1 item (Box Z-000003, Item 8)
    - Box Elder Canyon on the Salmon River, Idaho, circa 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000083, Item 15)
    - Box Elder Canyon on the Salmon River, Idaho, circa 1989 April; 1 item (Box P-000083, Item 16)
    - Junction of the Jefferson and Madison Rivers, Three Forks, Montana, circa 1988; 1 item (Box P-000083, Item 17)
    - Big Blackfoot River, Montana, circa 1988 July; 1 item (Box P-000083, Item 18)
    - Confluence of Crazy Woman Creek and Powder River, Wyoming, undated; 1 item (Box P-000083, Item 19)
  - Gaede Family and Friends Portraits, 1971-1988; 2 boxes
    Consists of mounted individual and group portrait photographs (eight 8x10" and one 15x19") of Marc and Marnie Gaede with family and friends, including their children, Ansel and Virginia Adams, Beaumont Newhall, and A.B. Guthrie, Jr. While most of the photographs were taken by Marc Gaede, several were taken by other photographers whose names are listed at the file-level.
    - Marc Gaede - "Monkey Wrencher" - Taken at Tuba City, 1971; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 1)
      Photograph taken by C. Bensen Hufford.
    - Marc Gaede, 1986 June; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 2)
      Photograph taken by Marnie Gaede. Printed 1986.
    - Marnie at Dead Horse Point, Utah, circa 1973 December; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 3)
    - Beaumont Newhall and Miles Gaede, 1988 June; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 4)
    - Ansel and Virginia Adams - Marnie, Miles, and Marcus - Adams House, Carmel, California, 1984 April; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 5)
    - Ansel Adams and Marc Gaede, circa 1974; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 6)
      Photographer unknown.
    - Ansel Adams and Marnie Gaede Portrait, circa 1984; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 7)
      Photograph taken by Alan Ross.
    - A.B. Guthrie, Jr., and Marc Gaede, Montana, 1988 January; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 8)
      Photograph taken by Carol Guthrie.
    - Marnie and Clouds, Chinle, Arizona, 1984; 1 item (Box P-000083, Item 20)
  - Miscellaneous Prints, 1973-1989 May 18; 2 boxes
    Consists of four mounted photographic prints (three 8x10" and one 11x14") that do not appear to be associated with a specific book project.
    - Sadie Adams, Hopi Potter, Keams Canyon, Arizona, 1977 March; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 9)
    - Untitled Photograph of Two Men in Front of "Cross Canyon" Building, undated; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 10)
    - Edward Abbey Memorial, Arches National Park, Utah, 1989 May 18; 1 item (Box P-000070, Item 11)
    - Abstract - Monument Valley, Arizona, circa 1973; 1 item (Box P-000061, Item 33)
- Photography, Archaeology, and Conservation Working Files, 1959-1997; 5 boxes
  Arranged by project in chronological order of publication, followed by general topical files.
  Consists of working files for Marc Gaede's photography books, many of which Marnie Gaede edited, as well as for Marc and Marnie Gaede's articles and book projects on archaeology and conservation and files on noted photographers and printers with whom Gaede worked. These files consist primarily of correspondence, agreements and contracts, financial and legal documents, progress reports, drafts of writings, publicity materials, photograph lists and captions, and film treatment notes. There are files of associated non-photographic materials for several books of Gaede's photography, including Camera, Spade and Pen (University of Arizona Press, 1980), Images from the Southwest (Chaco Press, 1986), Bordertowns (Chaco Press, 1988), and Images from the Great West (Chaco Press, 1990); as well as The Hopi Photographs (Chaco Press, 1986), a book of photographic reproductions Gaede made from the negatives of photographer Kate Cory (1861–1958); The Anasazi (Museum of Northern Arizona, 1977) by J. Richard Ambler, for which Gaede provided photographs; and Adventures in Conservation with Franklin D. Roosevelt (Northland, 1989), a book by Gaede's grandfather, Irving Brant. Also present are offprints of an archaeology article by Marc and Marnie Gaede, a copy of Marc Gaede's master's thesis on lithography processes, and files of correspondence and clippings on photographer Ansel Adams and novelist Edward Abbey, which reflect Gaede's working relationship with them. There are also several audiocassette tapes including recorded interviews and lectures by George Waters, Edith Hamlin, James Welch, and A.B. Guthrie, Jr.
  - "100 Years of Erosion at Poncho House", 1977; 1 folder (Box B-000836, Folder 1)
    Consists of three offprints of Marc and Marnie Gaede's article in Kiva (Vol. 43, No. 1).
  - The Anasazi: Contract Copies, 1977 May 2; 1 folder (Box B-000836, Folder 2)
  - Camera, Spade and Pen, 1974-1987; 1 box
    - Camera, Spade and Pen: Correspondence, Progress Reports, and Agreements, 1974-1977; 1 folder (Box B-000836, Folder 3)
    - Camera, Spade and Pen: Correspondence and Publicity, 1978-1987; 1 folder (Box B-000836, Folder 4)
  - Images from the Southwest, 1985-1987; 1 box
    - Images from the Southwest: Drafts and Image Lists, 1985; 1 folder (Box B-000836, Folder 5)
    - Images from the Southwest: Correspondence, Financial Papers, and Publicity, 1985-1987; 1 folder (Box B-000836, Folder 6)
  - Bordertowns, 1980-1997; 3 boxes
    - Bordertowns: Correspondence, Waivers, and Financial Records, 1983-1997; 1 folder (Box B-000836, Folder 7)
    - Bordertowns: Publicity, 1987-1995; 3 folders (Box B-000837, Folder 1-3)
    - Original Recording Bordertowns Epilogue, circa 1980-1987; 1 box (Box 40)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      AM 2018-104
      1 audiocassette tape containing an original recording from which the epilogue to Bordertowns was based. Recorded at the Police Department in Gallup, New Mexico. Side A: approximately 5 minutes.
      Conditions Governing Access
      For preservation reasons, physical access to original audio and visual media in a variety of magnetic and optic formats is restricted. The Special Collections does not have playback equipment and facilities, and all original media, especially in obsolete formats, must be digitally remastered or converted in accordance with prevailing preservation standards in order to be safely accessed. Subject to staffial approval, patrons may request duplicates of such original media, but will be responsible for both the cost of digital conversion and the cost of the duplicate, payable in advance. Public Services staff handles all such requests. Depending on the nature of the media, this process can take 4-6 weeks or longer.
  - The Hopi Photographs, 1959-1997; 2 boxes
    - The Hopi Photographs: Kate Cory Correspondence and Financial and Legal Papers, 1959-1987; 1 folder (Box B-000837, Folder 4)
    - The Hopi Photographs: Original Kate Cory Draft, 1985 July 15; 1 folder (Box B-000837, Folder 5)
    - The Hopi Photographs: Legal Correspondence, 1975-1997; 1 folder (Box B-000838, Folder 1)
    - The Hopi Photographs: Ben Hufford File on Kate Cory, 1975-1997; 1 folder (Box B-000838, Folder 2)
      Appears to be a copy of the legal correspondence in the preceding file.
    - The Hopi Photographs: Katy Cory Book Captions and Images, undated; 1 folder (Box B-000838, Folder 3)
    - The Hopi Photographs: Kate Cory Film Treatment, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box B-000838, Folder 4)
  - "The Expanded Range Graphic Lithography Process for Black and White Art Photography", 1988 January 6; 1 folder (Box B-000838, Folder 5)
    Bound copy of Marc Gaede's master's thesis for his MFA in Photography at the Art Center College of Design in Pasadena, California.
  - Adventures in Conservation with Franklin D. Roosevelt: Correspondence and Agreements, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box B-000838, Folder 6)
    Relates to the 1989 book by Irving Brant, Marc Gaede's grandfather. Includes a draft letter to Virginia Adams.
  - Images from the Great West, 1987-1994; 2 boxes
    - Images from the Great West: Correspondence, Financial Papers, and Publicity, 1987-1994; 1 folder (Box B-000838, Folder 7)
    - Images from the Great West: Drafts with Notes from A. B. Guthrie, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box B-000839, Folder 1)
    - Images from the Great West: Publicity, 1990-1992; 2 folders (Box B-000839, Folder 2-3)
  - Edward Abbey: Correspondence and Clippings, 1988-1993; 1 folder (Box B-000839, Folder 4)
    Includes correspondence with Clarke Abbey, Chuck Bowden, Ken Sanders, and Eric Temple, as well as a group of obituary clippings following Edward Abbey's death and a check from Marc Gaede to Edward Abbey.
  - Ansel Adams: Correspondence and Clippings, 1977-1991; 1 folder (Box B-000839, Folder 5)
    Includes correspondence with Ansel and Virginia Adams, including letters from Ansel Adams during the time Marc Gaede worked under him, as well as later correspondence regarding image permissions, as well as programs and clippings related to Ansel Adams.
  - Sound Recordings of Photographers, Printers, and Associates, 1987 March 4-May 31; 1 box
    - Interview with George Waters, 1987 March 4-April 14; 1 box
      4 audiocassette tapes containing an interview of George Waters, a master printer master who collaborated with Ansel Adams from 1969 to 1979.
      - George Waters, 1987 March 5; 1 box (Box 40)
        2 audiocassette tapes: Part 1 and 2 are on one tape, and Part 3 and 4 are on the second tape.
      - George Waters, 1987 April 14; 1 box (Box 40)
    - Edith Hamlin on Maynard Dixon, 1987 March 4; 1 box (Box 40)
      1 audiocassette tape (2 sides) containing an interview, conducted in San Francisco, with Edith Hamlin regarding her husband Maynard Dixon.
    - James Welch, "Fools Crow" / A.B. Guthrie, Jr., "Fair Land, Fair Land", 1987 May 31; 1 box (Box 40)
      1 audiocassette tape (2 sides) containing on Side A (45 minutes): James Welch lecture on "Fools Crow;" and on Side B (45 minutes): A.B. Guthrie, Jr., lecture on "Fair Land, Fair Land." The event was conducted at Hell Gate Writers, Inc. Missoula, Montana, and both lectures include introductions by Bill Bevis.
- Robert Sundance Working Files, 1910-1998; Sundance, Robert, 1927-1993; 21 boxes
  Arranged into four primary file groups.
  Consists of comprehensive working files for a biography of Robert Sundance, which was published by Chaco Press as Sundance: The Robert Sundance Story in 1994. Marc Gaede and Robert Sundance first met in 1986 after Sundance spoke out in defense of Gaede's controversial book Bordertowns, which depicted alcoholism in Native American communities. In 1990, Sundance and the Gaedes agreed to collaborate on Sundance's biography, which they worked on from 1990 to 1993, with Marc Gaede composing the text of the biography from recordings of Sundance telling his story and Marnie Gaede providing editorial guidance. Fifty-four audiocassette tapes containing recordings of Sundance's oral history are present, as well as transcriptions, drafts of the biography in both paper and digital form, and administrative correspondence regarding publishing and editorial matters. There is also a significant group of legal research files compiled and annotated by Sundance during the 1970s and 1980s, which include court documents, clippings, and publicity materials regarding his case, as well as other American Indian rights issues. A smaller group of personal and family papers of Robert Sundance includes other writings by him, correspondence, personal documents, and family and childhood photographs.
  Sundance, Robert, 1927-1993
  Biographical / Historical
  Robert Sundance was a Hunkpapa Lakota Sioux activist who was born Rupert Sibley McLaughlin in March 1927 in Wakpala, South Dakota, on the Standing Rock Sioux Reservation. Sundance struggled with alcoholism from a young age. After serving in the United States Navy and Air Force from 1943 to 1950, he lived itinerantly across the American West for the next several decades, often homeless and incarcerated hundreds of times for public drunkenness. When in the 1960s he found himself being routinely arrested on Skid Row in Los Angeles, he began a legal self-education program using resources he found in jail libraries. By the early 1970s he was writing dozens of petitions to the courts, largely writs of habeas corpus arguing that it was unconstitutional for the police to arrest people simply for suffering from the disease of alcoholism and for being too impoverished to have a place to live. When one of his petitions eventually reached the Center for Law in the Public Interest, a young lawyer named Timothy McFlynn agreed to take on Sundance's case.